Finding Aid for James V. Mansfield Papers
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
James V. Mansfield papers 1859-1933 1862-1864
Mansfield, James V. papers
Mansfield, James V., b. c. 1817
29 volumes and 13 loose items
wclmss001337
The James V. Mansfield papers include 27 volumes of bound letters and 2 account books. With the exception of two letters, each volume contains the outgoing correspondence of Mansfield, who was a "writing medium" by profession, and a prominent member of the spiritualist movement during the mid- to late-nineteenth century. The letters were sent to his wife and children in Chelsea, Massachusetts, when he lived in San Francisco, California, for two years. His letters provide detailed description of Civil War era San Francisco, and are an excellent source of common attitudes regarding women and various ethnic groups. Two alphabetized account books contain unfinished entries on his séances from December 24, 1860, to March 26, 1883.
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
1993 and 1996. M-2930, M-3219.3.
The collection is open for research.
Biography
James V. Mansfield (b. c. 1817) was known as a "writing medium," and a prominent member of the spiritualist movement during the mid- to late-nineteenth century. Born in Dudley, Massachusetts, Mansfield was one of many children of Jera Mansfield (b. c.1790) and Lucretia Corbin Mansfield (b. c.1795). Not much is known of his early life, though he eventually settled in Chelsea, Massachusetts, with his wife, Mary Hopkinson (b. c.1827), and two children, Mary Gertrude "Gertie" (b. c.1854) and John Worthington (1849-1933). The latter became a well-known artist, whose paintings are still extant. Mansfield endured many financial struggles, and was impelled at times to travel in search of work. This included trips to San Francisco, California, and to New York City.
Mansfield provided spirit communications solely through letter writing, and this earned him the title of the "spirit postmaster." Those who wished to communicate with the departed could do so in two ways: they could have a séance with him in person, or they could mail a letter to the spirit in care of Mansfield. In the latter case, Mansfield would provide answers to unopened letters. Being very confident in his abilities, he also referred to himself as a "test medium," providing free communications for skeptics.
Mansfield was both admired and loathed for his "talents." Allegedly satirizing him in his book Life on the Mississippi, Mark Twain writes, "If this man is not the paltriest fraud that lives, I owe him an apology." Though Mansfield claimed to have converted a number of people into "believers," and many wrote admiringly of his abilities, he could not escape the scrutiny of skeptics. In 1885, he was studied by the University of Pennsylvania's Seybert Commission, which was established to investigate spiritualist phenomena. After observing Mansfield, Dr. Horace Howard Furness of the Commission concluded in the official report that he was at best a charlatan, thus tarnishing his name.
The James V. Mansfield papers amount to approximately 10,000 pages of outgoing correspondence to his wife and children in Chelsea, Massachusetts. Spanning from March 7, 1862, to June 3, 1864, the letters cover Mansfield's journey to, as well as his two-year stay in, San Francisco, California. The collection's historical significance, however, is largely derived from Mansfield's meticulous recording of major events that occurred during this period, such as news of Civil War battles, earthquakes, and the S.S. Golden Gate disaster, and from his detailed descriptions of the cultural milieu of San Francisco between 1862 and 1864.
In his first journal, Mansfield recounts his journey from New York City to San Francisco. He traveled aboard the ship the North Star until he reached the Isthmus of Panama, and then continued the rest of his journey on the Sonora. He describes the deplorable conditions on the overly crowded ships, including shortages of food and clean drinking water, and flea and bedbug infestations in the sleeping quarters. He also reports his first impressions of San Francisco, such as the general appearance and attitudes of the people, as well as the climate and geography.
His correspondence is particularly instrumental in illuminating the social conditions and cultural life of San Francisco. Mansfield describes the diverse array of people he encountered, social attitudes, and ethnic tensions. In addition to indigenous peoples of California, immigrants from Mexico, China, Ireland, and Germany were all living in the city in substantial numbers. Those from China and Ireland comprised the largest immigrant groups that he observed. A large number of people had also traveled from the East Coast or the southern states to San Francisco. Some of these newcomers found work as miners or servants. Like Mansfield, most New Englanders came to California with the intention of staying only for a short period of time before returning home.
Although San Francisco was far removed from the operations of the Civil War, the people felt the impact of Confederate and Union victories and defeats. Likewise, Mansfield was deeply concerned by the war, and records his impressions of the news of battles as it was reported in San Francisco. Though California was part of the Union, Mansfield witnessed discrimination against free African Americans and frequently encountered anti-Union sentiments. He notes, "…they will not for a long time submit to allow the colored man or woman the same rights, same privileges as they themselves claim a Strong Southern feeling is Evident on the face of things here…" 19: 224. He provides examples of African Americans being barred from privileges the white people enjoyed, such as not being able to ride on steam engines and in horse carriages. One such case was brought before a municipal judge, who decided in favor of African Americans, granting them the right to use public transportation. Although such victories were possible in Civil War era San Francisco, racial segregation remained prevalent.
Mansfield observed vast differences between New Englanders and the people in California. Of the latter he writes, "…they are a hard set of people driving on from 4 oclock in the morning till 10 or 12 oclock at night, their general appearance is of Brown Complexion long hair, long whiskers and not more than one in 4 Ever shave; so you can imagine what for a looking people they are and all invariably Chew & Smoke Tobaco and drink the meanest Kinds of Whiskey. Consequently they swear much and their word is usually not worth a fig either…" 12: 115-116. Throughout the 27 journals, he provides a substantial amount of commentary on the indigenous people of California and Native Americans in general, of which his opinion is also not high. He thought Native Americans deliberately interfered with mail sent overland, especially when he had not received his wife's letters: "…the mails are to be conveyed by steam and not overland -- you see the trouble the Indians gave the mail carriers…" 1: 16-17. He did, however, recognize the atrocities white people committed against them, and later admitted that the Native Americans were not at fault for poor mail service.
Mansfield also provides a great deal of commentary on gender, noting differences between women on the East Coast and in San Francisco, especially in terms of appearance and dress. He was very conscious of feminine beauty, and was quick to note the physical aspect of a woman he encountered, and whether or not she was sufficiently attractive. He describes women from different ethnic backgrounds, including Chinese and Irish immigrant women. A great number of the former worked as prostitutes, while the latter were overwhelmingly employed as servants. In several instances, he discusses the hard life such women endured, especially those who worked as domestic servants. He also notes differences between the ways in which "Western" and "Eastern" women are treated, especially after noticing public displays of subservience among Chinese women.
Perhaps one of the most remarkable aspects of San Francisco was its markets. Mansfield found a variety of foods in San Francisco, which he had not seen before, or at least in such abundance. The overwhelming plentitude of fruits of all kinds included strawberries, cherries, apples, pineapples, bananas, figs, peaches, mangoes, pears, grapes, oranges, and watermelon. He also relates what he ate for his daily meals and the prices of food. Wine was widely available, which "…they drink here as they would water in the East…" 11: 83. Mansfield periodically visited his brother and sister-in-law, Jera (b. c.1825) and Nellie Mansfield (b. c.1836), who had moved to Napa several years before his arrival. In Napa, they planted a vineyard, where Mansfield was first exposed to the blossoming wine culture in California.
Mansfield became acquainted with a number of important people in San Francisco. The one who perhaps had the greatest influence on him was the preacher Thomas Starr King (1824-1864). Mansfield dutifully attended King's sermons every Sunday, and wrote about him profusely, including his impact on the city. He considered King to be one of the greatest minds of the 19th century. When he died on March 4, 1864, the entire city mourned, including Mansfield. Shortly after his death he wrote, "How lovely the Sabbath morning appears to those who were wont to attend Thomas Starr King's meeting there is no use his departure has created a vacuum that cannot be filled in the minds in the hearts of this people -- The Bell Tolls now for church service but it has lost its charm for me. It seems like tolling for the funeral requiem of the great good man rather than an invitation to listen to his heavenly soul stirring thoughts…" 26: 509. With the exception of his fellow spiritualist, Emma Hardinge Britten (1823-1899), Mansfield wrote of no other person with such admiration.
Spiritualism and the general religious community also figured prominently in his correspondence. Although he referred to himself as the "…notorious Spiritual Writing Medium…" 2:51, his being a public person did not always guarantee financial success. He did, nevertheless, procure enough business to send money to his family on a regular basis, via Wells Fargo and Company. Mansfield often gives detailed accounts of these séances, revealing the names and messages of the spirits. Likewise, he describes a variety of individuals who came to him to communicate with the departed, some wanting advice, others seeking comfort in the wake of the death of a loved one. He usually charged five dollars for a one-hour session, and three dollars for a half hour. Even the famous wished to utilize his talents, such as Mary Todd Lincoln (1818-1882). Only once, however, does he describe the process by which a spirit "entered" his body and commenced writing. He wrote communications in many different languages and alphabets, most of which, he claimed to not know. He often spoke of other mediums, especially his friend, the eminent clairvoyant and public speaker Emma Hardinge Britten. After much encouragement, Mansfield convinced her to travel to San Francisco, thinking her talents would earn her great success. Indeed, once in California, her lectures attracted sizeable crowds that rivaled those of Thomas Starr King.
As he was meticulous in his observations of San Francisco, so too did he keep detailed records of his séances. Also owned by the Clements Library are two alphabetized account books that originally belonged to Mansfield, containing entries on séances from December 24, 1860, to March 26, 1883. Volume 1 contains names and dates of séances of people with last names of the letters "A" through "B," but he never finished his entries. Inside the inner cover is a printed advertisement for Mansfield, which includes a lithograph of him. The rest of this volume, as well as volume 2, are blank, with the exception of two pages of the latter that were used in 1933 by an unknown individual.
In addition to these 29 volumes are 13 miscellaneous items that include two letters written in 1874 and 1875 to his son while he studied art in Paris. At this time, Mansfield was living in New York City. Two earlier letters to his daughter are also present, one written in 1859 and the other in 1860. Another letter that dates to 1877 is addressed to a grandson named Bertie. Among these items are also a lithograph of Mansfield and his business card.
The Mansfield collection is very valuable for the chronicling of Civil War era San Francisco, and for the insight it provides into the spiritualist movement. It is an excellent source of common attitudes regarding women and various ethnic groups. Although the lure of wealth drew many enterprising individuals to California, Mansfield's writings, above all, bring to light the many hardships endured by those endeavoring to attain such prosperity.
Subjects:
African Americans--California--San Francisco--History--19th century.; African Americans--California--Social Conditions--19th century.; African Americans--Legal status, laws, etc.--California--History--19th century.; Agriculture--California.; California--Climate.; California--Geography.; California--Social Life & customs--19th century.; Chinese Americans--California--San Francisco--History.; Chinese Americans--California--San Francisco--Social life and customs.; Death--United States--History--19th century.; Dogs--California.; Earthquakes--California--San Francisco.; Fleas--California--San Francisco.; Footbinding.; Fruit--California.; German Americans--California--History.; Gold mines & mining--California--History--19th century.; Hair.; Horses--California--San Francisco.; Indians of North America--1860-1870.; Indians of North America--California--History--19th century.; Irish Americans--California--History--19th century.; Irish Americans--California--San Francisco--Social conditions.; Italian Americans--California--San Francisco.; Markets--California--San Francisco.; Mediums--United States.; Murder--California--San Francisco--History--19th century.; Prices--California--San Francisco.; Prostitution--California--San Francisco.; Religious institutions--California--San Francisco Bay area.; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.)--History--19th century.; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.)--Social life and customs--19th century.; Séances--California--San Francisco.; Slavery--United States.; Spirit photography.; Spiritualism--United States--History--19th century.; Steamboats--California--San Francisco.; Steamboat disasters--United States--History--19th century.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Wells, Fargo & Company--History.; Wine and wine making--California--Napa Valley.; Women--California.; Women--Social conditions.; Women mediums.; Working class--California--San Francisco--Social conditions.
Genre Terms:
Account books.
- Correspondence
  - Volume 1: 1862 March 7-May 30 (Box 1)
  - Volume 2: 1862 May 31-June 27
  - Volume 3: 1862 June 29-July 10
  - Volume 4: 1862 July 28-August 09
  - Volume 5: 1862 August 11-August 20
  - Volume 6: 1862 August 21-August 30
  - Volume 7: 1862 September 1-September 10
  - Volume 8: 1862 September 11-September 22
  - Volume 9: 1862 September 20-September 30
  - Volume 10: 1862 October 11-October 19
  - Volume 11: 1862 October 20-November 22
  - Volume 12: 1862 November 18-December 8 (Box 2)
  - Volume 13: 1862 December 19-1863 January 9
  - Volume 14: 1863 February 23-March 10
  - Volume 15: 1863 March 11-April 1
  - Volume 16: 1863 April 2-April 22
  - Volume 17: 1863 April 23-May 12
  - Volume 18: 1863 May 13-May 22
  - Volume 19: 1863 May 23-June 12
  - Volume 20: 1863 June 13-July 2
  - Volume 21: 1863 July 3-July 20 (Box 3)
  - Volume 22: 1863 July 22-August 12
  - Volume 23: 1863 August 13-September 2
  - Volume 24: 1863 September 4-September 28
  - Volume 25: 1863 November 9-December 17
  - Volume 26: 1864 February 4-March 23
  - Volume 27: 1864 April 23-June 3
- Account books
  - Volume 28: 1860 December 24-1883 March 26 (Box 4)
  - Volume 29: 1933 April 28-June 1
- Volume 30: 13 Loose items, 1859 November 18-1877 July 8, undated
Item located in Book Division:
Britten, Emma Hardinge.Funeral oration on the late Rev. T. Starr King to be delivered by Miss Emma Hardinge, at Platt's New Music Hall, Thursday evening, March 10th, at 8 o'lock, P.M. Clements Broadsides Small.
Materials at other institutions:
John W. Mansfield papers (1864-1931), Archives of American Art, The Smithsonian Institution.
Seybert Commission records (1884-1922), University of Pennsylvania, Franklin Library.
Britten, Emma Hardinge. Modern American spiritualism: A twenty years' record of the communion between earth and the world of spirits. New York, 1870.
Cox, Robert S. Body and Soul: A sympathetic history of American Spiritualism. University of Virginia Press: Charlottesville, 2003.
Kerr, Howard. Mediums, and spirit-rappers, and roaring radicals; Spiritualism in American literature, 1850-1900.. University of Illinois Press: Urbana, 1972.
Spence, Lewis. Encyclopedia of Occultism and Parapsychology, Part 2. Gale Research Inc.: Detroit, 1991.
Twain, Mark. Life on the Mississippi. J.R. Osgood & Company: Boston, 1883.
Wolfe, Napoleon Bonaparte. Startling Facts in Modern Spiritualism. Religio-Philosophical Publishing House: Chicago, 1875.
The following lists and indexes are located below:
1. List of personal names.
2. List of geographical locations.
3. Partial subject index (with textual references)
4. Partial name index (with textual references)
5. Partial geographical index (with textual references)
List of Personal Names
Andrew, John Albion, 1818-1867.
Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887.
Beecher, Lyman, 1775-1863.
Bellows, Henry Whitney, 1814-1882.
Britten, Emma Hardinge, 1823-1899.
Brown, Charles Farrar (Artemus Ward), 1834-1867.
Brown, John, 1800-1859.
Brownlow, William Gannaway, 1805-1877.
Butler, Benjamin F., 1818-1893.
Child, Asaph Bemis, 1813-1879.
Davis, Andrew Jackson, 1826-1910.
Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889.
Edwards, Amasa, 1814-1885.
Edwards, Matilda "Mattie", 1821-1884.
Farnham, Eliza, 1815-1864.
Fitch, Col. H.S.
Forster, Thomas Gales, 1816-1886.
Fremont, John Charles, 1813-1890.
Grant, Ulysses S., 1822-1885.
Hooker, Joseph, 1814-1879.
Kalakaua I, 1836-1891.
King, Edith, b. c. 1851.
King, Julia Wiggin, b. c. 1828.
King, Thomas Starr, 1824-1864.
Lee, Robert E., 1807-1870.
Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.
Lincoln, Mary Todd, 1818-1882.
Macondray, Capt. Frederick William, 1803-1862.
Mansfield, Bertie.
Mansfield, Daniel.
Mansfield, James Valentine, b. c. 1817.
Mansfield, Jera M., b. c. 1825.
Mansfield, John Worthington, 1849-1933.
Mansfield, Mary Gertrude "Gertie", b. c. 1854.
Mansfield, Mary Hopkinson, b. c. 1827.
Mansfield, Ellen "Nellie" Greenwood Estabrook, b. c. 1836.
Mansfield, Walter D., b. c. 1860.
McClellan, George Brinton, 1826-1885.
McClellan, R. Guy.
McDougal, Governor John, 1818-1866.
Montez, Lola, 1821-1861.
Napoleon III (Charles Louis Napoleon Bonaparte), 1808-1873.
Owen, James Jerome, 1827-1895.
Peebles, James Martin, 1822-1922.
Rowe, Gen. George.
Stow, Marietta L., d. 1902.
Stidger, O.B.
Strickland, Edward F.
Twiggs, David Emanuel, 1790-1862.
Young, Brigham, 1801-1877.
List of Geographical Locations
Alcatraz Island, California.
Baltimore, Maryland.
Benicia, California.
Boston, Massachusetts.
Chelsea, Massachusetts.
Denver, Colorado.
Grass Valley, California.
Marysville, California.
Napa, California.
New York City, New York.
Paris, France.
Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Sacramento, California.
San Francisco, California.
Sierra Nevada Mountains, California.
Sonoma, California.
Virginia City, Nevada.
Washoe County, Nevada.
Yuba County, California.
Partial Subject Index
African Americans--California--San Francisco--History--19th Century
16: 67-71
23: 233
African Americans--California--Social Conditions--19th century
10: 97
15: 280-281, 396
16: 67-68
17: 486-494
19: 222-228
21: 199
23: 233
24: 300-301
African Americans--Legal status, laws, etc.--California--History--19th century
19: 222-224
Agriculture--California
11: 165
13: 43
California--Climate
2: 175
8: 149-150
14: 76-78
16: 207, 512
California--Geography
4: 46-48, 75-79, 137-138
11: 80-81
13: 46-47, 96-97
16: 512
20: 127
24: 270, 315-317
California--Social Life & customs--19th century
Passim, but especially
1: 46-47
2: 319
12: 115-117
20: 140
22: 568
26: 481
27: 442
Chinese Americans--California--San Francisco—History
13: 163-168, 320
Chinese Americans--California--San Francisco--Social life and customs
1: 327-329
2: 289
10: 48-54
13: 77-78
15: 283-285
22: 487-488
Death--United States--History--19th century
passim
Dogs--California
2: 127-132
5: 186
6: 137-140
17: 166-167
Earthquakes--California--San Francisco
9: 187
26: 169-171, 198-198, 304, 321, 326
27: 463-463
Fleas--California--San Francisco
2: 18
4: 127
9: 46
15: 159-161
17: 326
19: 37
23: 63-67
Footbinding
10: 51-54
Fruit--California
1: 132-133, 270, 347
2: 175
4: 158
6: 39
8: 32-33
9: 57
14: 76
16: 44
17: 38
19: 133, 251
20: 21, 161-167, 280-281
21: 201
22: 564-568
24: 318-319
27: 600
German Americans--California--History
14: 153
24: 41-43
Gold mines & mining--California--History--19th century
1: 347
6: 78-80
8: 71
13: 4-5, 14-15, 22-26
15: 3-6, 199-205, 316-319
Hair
2: 88
17: 376-380
20: 339-343
Horses--California--San Francisco
8: 11-13
9: 189-192
12: 71-75
13: 19-22
17: 239
Indians of North America--1860-1870
2: 228
6: 127-129
16: 88-89
20: 117-118, 202-205
21: 206
22: 118
27: 469, 570
Indians of North America--California--History--19th century
1: 291
2: 144, 268, 287-288, 309-310
12: 117-120
20: 409
21: 123-124, 206
27: 469, 570
Irish Americans--California--History--19th century
16: 72
26: 462
Irish Americans--California--San Francisco--Social conditions
4: 105-110
16: 72
21: 84
22: 487-488
23: 355-357
Italian Americans--California--San Francisco
23: 189
Jews--California--San Francisco
15: 273-277, 371
16: 7
Markets--California--San Francisco
9: 57
14: 78-79
15: 230
21: 201
22: 564-567
24: 318-319
27: 600
Mediums--United States
Passim, but especially
15: 36-40
17: 213
Murder--California--San Francisco--History--19th century
17: 213
21: 15-19, 45-48
26: 198-200
Prices--California--History
1: 136, 176
8: 32-33
16: 72, 116
19: 105
21: 366
23: 145
25: 117, 181
27: 254
Prostitution--California--San Francisco
15: 283-285
16: 214
20: 175-176
Religious institutions--California--San Francisco Bay area
5: 203-215
12: 155
San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.)--History--19th century
passim
San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.)--Social life and customs--19th century
passim
Séances--California--San Francisco
Passim, but especially
2: 95
11: 104-105
14: 35
20: 246-250
23: 24, 135-136, 244-245
28: passim
Slavery--United States
15: 282-283
25: 327
Spirit photography
13: 66-67; 525
14: 42
15: 164, 235-238
Spiritualism--United States--History--19th century
Passim, but especially
3: 21-37
4: 229-230
5: 28-30
8: 100-102, 116-118
10: 9-12
12: 54-61, 86-90
13: 54-59, 494
15: 26-29, 229, 402-403
16: 161-169
20: 294-296
Steamboats--California--San Francisco
1: 1-20, 136, 283-284
2: 175
17: 136
20: 405
24: 48
27: 601
Steamboat disasters--United States--History--19th century
4: 220-242, 259-260
5: 9-16, 33-34
14: 153
21: 259
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Passim, but especially
1: 353-354
3: 123-124
4: 99-101, 152-155, 194-198
5: 35, 96-98, 121-124, 134-146
6: 50-52, 70-71, 94-95, 108-109, 141-143
7: 11-12, 64-65, 83-86, 111, 123-124, 151-153, 156-160, 170, 181-188
8: 2-4, 30-31, 135-136 143-144
9: 199-200
11: 132-134
12: 180-183
13: 44-50, 384-395, 466-70, 513-515
14: 21-24
15: 79-88, 136-141 144-145, 198-199, 385-387
16: 5-6, 31-39
17: 284, 467-477
19: 29
20: 72-76
21: 41 54-58
22: 48, 127, 130-131, 278, 284
24: 144, 250-251
25: 327
Wells, Fargo & Company--History
passim
Wine and wine making--California--Napa Valley
11: 163-167